The urban explosion
إن التوسع المدني
of the last years of economic boom
في السنوات الأخيرة من الطفرة الاقتصادية
also produced dramatic marginalization,
قد أدّى أيضاً إلى تهميش كبير،
resulting in the explosion of slums
نتجت عنه زيادة كبيرة في الأحياء الفقيرة
in many parts of the world.
في أجزاء كثيرة من العالم.
This polarization of enclaves of mega-wealth
هذا الاستقطاب بين المقاطعات الفاحشة الثراء
surrounded by sectors of poverty
المحاطة بقطاعات فقيرة
and the socioeconomic inequalities they have engendered
وعدم المساواة الاجتماعي-الاقتصادي الذي ولّده
is really at the center of today's urban crisis.
هو حقا أساس الأزمة المدنية اليوم.
But I want to begin tonight
لكني أريد أن أبدأ الليلة
by suggesting that this urban crisis
باقتراح أن هذه الأزمة المدنية
is not only economic or environmental.
هي ليست فقط اقتصادية أو بيئية.
It's particularly a cultural crisis,
إنها بالتحديد أزمة ثقافية،
a crisis of the institutions
أزمة المؤسسات
unable to reimagine the stupid ways
الغير قادرة على إعادة تصور الطرق الغبية
which we have been growing,
التي ظللنا نزيد فيها،
unable to challenge the oil-hungry,
وغير قادرين على تحدي المدنية الأنانية،
selfish urbanization that have perpetuated
المتعطشة للنفط التي خلّدت
cities based on consumption,
مدنا قائمة على الاستهلاك،
from southern California to New York to Dubai.
من جنوب كاليفورنيا إلى نيويورك إلى دبي.
So I just really want to share with you a reflection
لذا أريد حقاً أن أشارككم بفكرة
that the future of cities today
أن يعتمد مستقبل المدن
depends less on buildings
اليوم على البناء أقل
and, in fact, depends more
وفي الحقيقة، أن يعتمد أكثر
on the fundamental reorganization of socioeconomic relations,
على المؤسسة الجوهرية للعلاقات الاجتماعية-الاقتصادية،
that the best ideas in the shaping
أن أفضل الأفكار في تشكيل
of the city in the future
المدينة في المستقبل
will not come from enclaves of economic power
لن تأتي من مقاطعات ذات القوة الاقتصادية
and abundance,
ومن الوفرة،
but in fact from sectors of conflict and scarcity
لكن بالحقيقة من قطاعات الصراعات والشّح
from which an urgent imagination
من حيث يستطيع خيال طارئ
can really inspire us to rethink urban growth today.
أن يلهمنا حقاً لإعادة التفكير بالازدهار المدني اليوم.
And let me illustrate what I mean
ودعني أبين ما أعني
by understanding or engaging sites of conflict
بفهم أو مشاركة المناطق تحت الصراع
as harboring creativity, as I briefly introduce you
كمصدر للإبداع، بينما أقدم لكم بشكل مختصر
to the Tijuana-San Diego border region,
المنطقة الحدودية بين سان دييجو- تيخوانا،
which has been the laboratory to rethink my practice as an architect.
والذي أصبح مختبر لإعادة التفكير بمهنتي كمهندس معماري.
This is the wall, the border wall,
هذا هو الحائط، حائط الحدود،
that separates San Diego and Tijuana,
الذي يفصل سان دييجو عن تيخوانا،
Latin America and the United States,
أمريكا اللّاتينية والولايات المتحدة الأمريكية،
a physical emblem
إنه رمز ملموس
of exclusionary planning policies
لسياسات التخطيط الإقصائية
that have perpetuated the division
الذي مكّنت انقسام
of communities, jurisdictions
المجتمعات وسلطات الدول
and resources across the world.
والموارد حول العالم.
In this border region, we find
في هذه المنطقة الحدودية، نجد
some of the wealthiest real estate,
بعض أغلى العقارات،
as I once found in the edges of San Diego,
كما وجدت مرة من المرات في أطراف سان دييجو،
barely 20 minutes away
بالكاد 20 دقيقة من
from some of the poorest settlements in Latin America.
بعض أفقر المستوطنات في أمريكا اللّاتينية.
And while these two cities have the same population,
وبينما لهاتين المدينتين نفس عدد السكان،
San Diego has grown six times larger than Tijuana
فإن سان دييجو فد نمت ست مرات أكثر من تيخوانا
in the last decades,
في العقود الأخيرة،
immediately thrusting us to confront
وبشكل فوري عرضنا ذلك لمواجهة
the tensions and conflicts
الاحتقانات والصراعات
between sprawl and density,
بين التمدد والكثافة،
which are at the center of today's discussion
واللتان هما محور حديث اليوم
about environmental sustainability.
عن الاستدامة البيئية.
So I've been arguing in the last years
أنا أجادل أنه وفي السنوات الأخيرة
that, in fact, the slums of Tijuana can teach a lot
الأحياء الفقيرة لتيجوانا، في الحقيقة، يمكن أن تعلم الكثير
to the sprawls of San Diego
للتوسعات في سان دييجو
when it comes to socioeconomic sustainability,
بشأن الاستدامة الاجتماعية- الاقتصادية،
that we should pay attention and learn
أننا بحاجة إلى التعلم من والإنتباه إلى
from the many migrant communities
العديد من المجتمعات المهاجرة
on both sides of this border wall
على جانبي هذا الحائط الحدودي
so that we can translate their informal processes
كي نستطيع ترجمة عملياتهم العرفية،
of urbanization.
للتمدن.
What do I mean by the informal in this case?
ما الذي أعنيه بالعرفي في هذه الحالة؟
I'm really just talking about
إنني في الحقيقة أتكلم فقط عن
the compendium of social practices of adaptation
خلاصة عاداتهم الاجتماعية الخاصة بالتأقلم
that enable many of these migrant communities
التي تمكن العديد من هذه المجتمعات المهاجرة
to transgress imposed political and economic recipes
من تجاوز القوانين السياسية والاقتصادية المفروضة
of urbanization.
للتمدن.
I'm talking simply about the creative intelligence
إنني ببساطة أتكلم عن الذكاء الإبداعي
of the bottom-up,
المنبثق من القاعدة،
whether manifested in the slums of Tijuana
سواء ظاهريا في الأحياء الفقيرة لتيخوانا
that build themselves, in fact, with the waste of San Diego,
التي تبني نفسها، في الحقيقة، من مخلفات سان دييجو،
or the many migrant neighborhoods in Southern California
أو أحياء المهاجرين الكثيرة في كاليفورنيا الجنوبية،
that have begun to be retrofitted with difference
التي بدأت في التعديل وفقاً للتغييرات
in the last decades.
في العقود الأخيرة.
So I've been interested as an artist
إذاً إنني مهتم كفنان
in the measuring, the observation,
بقياس وبملاحظة،
of many of the trans-border informal flows
العديد من التنقلات الغير رسمية التي تحدث عبر الحدود
across this border:
عبر هذا الحد:
in one direction, from south to north,
في اتجاه، من الجنوب إلى الشمال،
the flow of immigrants into the United States,
يتدفق المهاجرون إلى الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية،
and from north to south the flow of waste
ومن الشمال إلى الجنوب تتدفق النفايات
from southern California into Tijuana.
من كاليفورنيا الجنوبية إلى تيخوانا.
I'm referring to the recycling
إنني أشير إلى إعادة تدوير
of these old post-war bungalows
هذه البيوت من القش القديمة منذ فترة ما بعد الحرب
that Mexican contractors bring to the border
التي يحضرها المقاولون المكسيكيون إلى الحدود
as American developers are disposing of them
بينما المطورون الأمريكيون يتخلصون منها
in the process of building a more inflated version
ضمن عملية بناء نسخة مسطحة أكثر
of suburbia in the last decades.
للضواحي في العقود الماضية.
So these are houses waiting to cross the border.
إذاً هذه منازل تنتظر عبور الحدود.
Not only people cross the border here,
ليس فقط الأشخاص هي من تعبر الحدود هنا،
but entire chunks of one city move to the next,
لكن أجزاء كاملة من مدينة تنتقل إلى أخرى،
and when these houses are placed on top of these steel frames,
وعندما يتم وضع هذه البيوت على الأطر الفولاذية هاته،
they leave the first floor to become the second
يدعون الطابق الأول ليصبح الثاني،
to be in-filled with more house,
يتم شغله بالمزيد من المنازل،
with a small business.
مع تجارة صغيرة.
This layering of spaces and economies
هذه الطبقية في المساحات والأمور المالية
is very interesting to notice.
من المثير جداً ملاحظتها.
But not only houses, also small debris
لكن ليست المنازل وحسب، بل أيضاً النفايات صغيرة
from one city, from San Diego, to Tijuana.
من مدينة، من سان دييجو، إلى تخوانا.
Probably a lot of you have seen the rubber tires
على الأغلب قد رأى الكثير منكم الإطارات المطاطية
that are used in the slums to build retaining walls.
التي تستخدم في الأحياء الفقيرة لبناء حوائط عازلة.
But look at what people have done here in conditions
لكن انظر إلى ما فعل الناس هنا في ظروف
of socioeconomic emergency.
اجتماعية-اقتصادية طارئة.
They have figured out how to peel off the tire,
لقد اكتشفوا كيف ينزعون أغلفة الإطارات،
how to thread it and interlock it
وكيف يخيطونها و يداخلوها
to construct a more efficient retaining wall.
لبناء حائط عازل أكثر فعالية.
Or the garage doors that are brought
أو أبواب المرآب التي أحضرت
from San Diego in trucks
من سان دييجو في الشاحنات
to become the new skin of emergency housing
لتكون الطبقة الجديدة للملاجئ
in many of these slums
في الكثير من هذه الأحياء الفقيرة
surrounding the edges of Tijuana.
المحيطة بحدود تيخونا.
So while, as an architect,
إذا بينما، كمهندس معماري،
this is a very compelling thing to witness,
هذا يعد أمرا جذابا جداً للمشاهدة،
this creative intelligence,
هذا الذكاء المبدع،
I also want to keep myself in check.
أريد أيضاً أن أبقى واقعيا.
I don't want to romanticize poverty.
لا أريد أن أجمّل الفقر.
I just want to suggest
أريد فقط اقتراح
that this informal urbanization
أن هذه المدنية العرفية
is not just the image of precariousness,
هي فقط صورة لهشاشة الموضوع،
that informality here, the informal,
لانعدام الرسمية، الغير رسمي،
is really a set of socioeconomic and political procedures
إنه حقاً مجموعة من الإجراءات الاجتماعية – الاقتصادية والسياسية
that we could translate as artists,
والتي يمكننا ترجمتها كفنانين
that this is about a bottom-up urbanization
على أنها مدنية من القاع إلى الأعلى
that performs.
التي تؤدي.
See here, buildings are not important
انظر هنا، إن الأبنية ليست مهمة
just for their looks,
لمنظرها وحسب،
but, in fact, they are important for what they can do.
لكن، في الحقيقة، هي مهمة لما يمكن أن تؤديه.
They truly perform as they transform through time
إنها حقاً تؤدي بينما هي تتحول خلال الزمن
and as communities negotiate
بينما تتناقش المجتمعات
the spaces and boundaries and resources.
في المساحات والحدود والموارد.
So while waste flows southbound,
إذا بينما تتدفق النفايات إلى الجنوب،
people go north in search of dollars,
يسافر الناس إلى الشمال بحثاً عن المال،
and most of my research has had to do
وأغلب بحثي متعلق
with the impact of immigration
بأثر الهجرة
in the alteration of the homogeneity
في تغير تجانس
of many neighborhoods in the United States,
العديد من الأحياء في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية،
particularly in San Diego.
بالتحديد في سان دييجو.
And I'm talking about how this begins to suggest
وأنا أتحدث عن كيف أصبحت هاته تقترح
that the future of Southern California
أن مستقبل كاليفورنيا الجنوبية
depends on the retrofitting
يعتمد على التعديل
of the large urbanization -- I mean, on steroids --
المدنية الكبيرة – أعني، التي تستخدم المنشطات --
with the small programs,
مع البرامج الصغيرة،
social and economic.
الاجتماعية والاقتصادية.
I'm referring to how immigrants,
إنني أشير إلى كيف أن المهاجرين،
when they come to these neighborhoods,
عندما يأتون إلى هذه الأحياء،
they begin to alter the one-dimensionality
يبدؤوا بتغير البضائع والممتلكات
of parcels and properties
أحادية البعد
into more socially and economically complex systems,
إلى أنظمة اجتماعية و اقتصادية أكثر تعقيدا،
as they begin to plug an informal economy into a garage,
بينما يبدؤون بإدخال اقتصاد غير رسمي إلى مرآب،
or as they build an illegal granny flat
أو بينما يبنون شقة إضافية بشكل غير قانوني
to support an extended family.
لإيواء عائلة كبيرة.
This socioeconomic entrepreneurship
إدارة الأعمال هذه ذات الطابع الاجتماعي-الاقتصادي
on the ground within these neighborhoods
على الأرض بين هذه الأحياء
really begins to suggest ways of translating that
تبدأ حقيقة باقتراح طرق لترجمة ذلك
into new, inclusive and more equitable
إلى سياسات جديدة، متضمنة وأكثر
land use policies.
عدالة في استخدام الأراضي.
So many stories emerge from these dynamics
العديد من هذه القصص تنبثق من هذه الديناميكيات
of alteration of space,
لتغيير المساحة،
such as &amp;quot;the informal Buddha,&amp;quot;
مثل "بوذا الغير رسمي"؛
which tells the story of a small house
الذي يحكي قصة بيت صغير
that saved itself, it did not travel to Mexico,
الذي حما نفسه، ولم يسافر إلى المكسيك،
but it was retrofitted in the end
لكن تم تعديله في النهاية
into a Buddhist temple,
إلى معبد بوذي،
and in so doing,
وبفعل ذلك،
this small house transforms or mutates
هذا البيت الصغير يتحول أو يصاب بطفرة
from a singular dwelling
من سكن فردي
into a small, or a micro, socioeconomic
إلى بناء تحتي صغير، أو مجهري، اجتماعي- اقتصادي
and cultural infrastructure inside a neighborhood.
وثقافي في حي سكني.
So these action neighborhoods, as I call them,
إذاً هذه الأحياء الحركية، كما أسميها،
really become the inspiration
تصبح حقاً إلهاما
to imagine other interpretations of citizenship
لتخيل تفاسير أخرى للمواطنة
that have less to do, in fact,
التي تعتمد بشكل أقل، في الحقيقة،
with belonging to the nation-state,
على الانتماء إلى ولاية – أمة،
and more with upholding the notion of citizenship
و بشكل أكبر على التمسك بفكرة المواطنة
as a creative act
كفعل إبداعي
that reorganizes institutional protocols
الذي يعترف بالإجراءات المؤسسية
in the spaces of the city.
في مساحات المدينة.
As an artist, I've been interested, in fact,
كفنان، لقد كنت مهتم، بالحقيقة،
in the visualization of citizenship,
بالتصوير المرئي للمواطنة،
the gathering of many anecdotes, urban stories,
بجمع العبر العديدة، القصص المدنية،
in order to narrativize the relationship
من أجل الإخبار عن العلاقة
between social processes and spaces.
بين العمليات الاجتماعية و المساحات.
This is a story of a group of teenagers
هذه قصة مجموعة من المراهقين
that one night, a few months ago,
الذين في ليلة ما، قبل بضعة أشهر،
decided to invade this space under the freeway
قرروا أن يحتلوا هذه المساحة تحت الطريق السريع
to begin constructing their own skateboard park.
للبدء في بناء منتزه تزلج خاص بهم.
With shovels in hand, they started to dig.
و باستخدام المجارف، بدأوا بالحفر.
Two weeks later, the police stopped them.
بعد أسبوعين، أوقفتهم الشرطة.
They barricaded the place,
وأغلقوا المكان،
and the teenagers were evicted,
وأجلوا المراهقين،
and the teenagers decided to fight back,
وقرر المراهقون المقاومة
not with bank cards or slogans
لكن ليس ببطاقاتهم البنكية أو الشعارات
but with constructing a critical process.
لكن بتخطيط عملية دقيقة.
The first thing they did was to recognize
أول ما فعلوه كان التعرف على
the specificity of political jurisdiction
تخصص السلطة القضائية
inscribed in that empty space.
التي تتبعها هذه المساحة الفارغة.
They found out that they had been lucky
لقد وجدوا أنه لحسن حظهم
because they had not begun to dig
أنهم لم يبدؤوا بالحفر
under Caltrans territoy.
أسفل إقليم كالترانز.
Caltrans is a state agency that governs the freeway,
كالترانز هي وكالة تابعة للولاية التي تحكم الطريق السريع،
so it would have been very difficult to negotiate with them.
إذاً كان من الصعب جداً مناقشتهم.
They were lucky, they said, because they began
قالوا بأنهم كانوا محظوظين، لأنهم بدأوا
to dig under an arm of the freeway
بالحفر أسفل فرع من الطريق السريع
that belongs to the local municipality.
الذي هو ملك للبلدية المحلية.
They were also lucky, they said,
لقد كانوا أيضاُ محظوظين، كما قالوا،
because they began to dig in a sort of
لأنهم بدأوا بالحفر بشكل يشبه
Bermuda Triangle of jurisdiction,
مثلث برمودا من السلطات القضائية،
between port authority, airport authority,
بين سلطة الموانئ وسلطة المطار،
two city districts, and a review board.
ومقاطعتي مدنيتين، ولجنة مراجعة.
All these red lines are the invisible
كل هذه الخطوط الحمراء هي
political institutions that were inscribed
المؤسسات السياسية الخفية التي نقشت
in that leftover empty space.
في تلك المساحة المتروكة الفارغة.
With this knowledge, these teenagers
مع هذه المعرفة، واجه هؤلاء
as skaters confronted the city.
المراهقين كمتزلجين المدينة.
They came to the city attorney's office.
لقد جاؤوا إلى مكتب محامي المدينة.
The city attorney told them
أخبرهم محامي المدينة
that in order to continue the negotiation
أنه من أجل الاستمرار بالمناقشة
they had to become an NGO,
كان يجب عليهم أن يصبحوا منظمة غير حكومية،
and of course they didn't know what an NGO was.
و بالطبع لم يكونوا يعرفون ما تعنيه هيئة غير حكومية.
They had to talk to their friends in Seattle
كان عليهم التكلم مع أصدقائهم في سياتل
who had gone through the same experience.
الذين مرّوا بنفس التجربة.
And they began to realize the necessity
وبدأوا بإدراك أهمية
to organize themselves even deeper
تنظيم نفسهم بشكل أعمق
and began to fundraise, to organize budgets,
وبدأوا بجمع التبرعات، وبتنظيم الميزانية،
to really be aware of all the knowledge
وبإدراك كل المعرفة
embedded in the urban code in San Diego
المتداخلة بالقانون المدني لسان دييجو
so that they could begin to redefine
حتى يستطيعوا إعادة تعريف
the very meaning of public space in the city,
المعنى الدقيق للمساحات العامة في المدينة،
expanding it to other categories.
وتوسيعها لتشمل تصنيفات أخرى.
At the end, the teenagers won the case
في النهاية، فاز المراهقون بالقضية
with that evidence, and they were able
بذلك الدليل، وأصبحوا قادرين
to construct their skateboard park
على بناء منتزه التزلج الخاص بهم.
under that freeway.
أسفل الطريق السريع ذلك.
Now for many of you, this story
الآن بالنسبة للعديد منكم، قد تبدو
might seem trivial or naive.
هذه القصة سخيفة أو ساذجة.
For me as an architect, it has become
بالنسبة لي كمهندس معماري، لقد أصبحت
a fundamental narrative,
رواية أساسية،
because it begins to teach me
لأنها بدأت بتعليمي
that this micro-community
أن هذه المجتمع المجهري
not only designed another category of public space
لم يصمم فقط تصنيفا جديدا للمساحة العامة
but they also designed the socioeconomic protocols
بل أيضاً قاموا بتصميم الإجراءات الاجتماعية - الاقتصادية
that were necessary to be inscribed in that space
التي كانت مهمة لتنقش في تلك المساحة
for its long-term sustainability.
من أجل استدامتها لأمد طويل.
They also taught me
لقد علموني أيضاً
that similar to the migrant communities
أنه وكما هو الحال في المجتمعات المهاجرة
on both sides of the border,
على جانبي الحدود،
they engaged conflict itself as a creative tool,
استخدموا الصراع نفسه كأداة إبداعية،
because they had to produce a process
لأنه كان عليهم إنتاج عملية
that enabled them to reorganize resources
قد مكنتهم من إعادة ترتيب موارد
and the politics of the city.
وسياسات المدينة.
In that act, that informal,
بذلك الفعل ذلك الخرق الغير رسمي،
bottom-up act of transgression,
للقوانين الذي بدأ من الأسفل نحو الأعلى،
really began to trickle up
قد بدأ بالفعل
to transform top-down policy.
بتحويل سياسة الأعلى نحو الأسفل.
Now this journey from the bottom-up
الآن هذه الرحلة من الأسفل إلى الأعلى
to the transformation of the top-down
لتحويل الأعلى إلى الأسفل
is where I find hope today.
هي حيث أجد الأمل اليوم.
And I'm thinking of how these modest alterations
وأنا أفكر بكيف يمكن لهذه التغيرات المتواضعة
with space and with policy
بالمساحة والسياسة
in many cities in the world,
في المدن المختلفة في العالم،
in primarily the urgency
وبشكل رئيسي في استعجالية
of a collective imagination
مخيلة جماعية
as these communities
بينما هذه المجتمعات
reimagine their own forms of governance,
تعيد تصور أشكال الحكم الخاصة بها،
social organization, and infrastructure,
التنظيم الاجتماعي والبنية التحتية،
really is at the center
إنها حقا أساس
of the new formation
التكوين الجديد
of democratic politics of the urban.
للسياسات الديموقراطية لمدنية.
It is, in fact, this that could become the framework
هذا، في الحقيقة، هو ما يمكن أن يصبح إطار عمل
for producing new social
لإيجاد مساواة جديدة اجتماعية
and economic justice in the city.
واقتصادية في المدينة.
I want to say this and emphasize it,
أريد أن أقول هذا و أن أؤكد عليه،
because this is the only way I see
لأن هذه هي الطريقة الوحيدة التي أراها
that can enable us to move
والتي تمكننا من الانتقال
from urbanizations of consumption
من تمدين الاستهلاك
to neighborhoods of production today.
إلى أحياء الإنتاج اليوم.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)